<sapia:page title="Licensing" xmlns:sapia="http://www.sapia-oss.org/2003/XSL/Transform">

  <sapia:vmenu>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus Home" href="index.html"/>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus Guide" href="CorusGuide.pdf"/>
  </sapia:vmenu>

  <sapia:sect1 title="License">
    <sapia:section>
      <sapia:path name="home" href="../../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="projects" />
      <sapia:path name="corus" href="home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="license" />
    </sapia:section>
    <sapia:sect-desc>
      <p>The Corus source code has been subdivided into two modules:</p> 

      <p>
        <b>1)</b> A “client” module, released under the 
        <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0.html">Apache 2.0 license</a>, 
        which produces a library (jar file) that can be placed into the 
        classpath of client applications, allowing these applications to 
        connect to Corus instances and use the Corus server API directly
        (a rarely necessary thing, unless one wants to develop his own tools
        for interacting with Corus).
      </p>
      <p> 
        <b>2)</b> A “server” module, released under the 
        <a href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-3.0-standalone.html">GPL 3.0</a>, 
        which strictly consists of the server-side Corus classes, which client applications 
        do NOT need in their classpath. This module depends on the client 
        module, for it implements some of the interfaces in it. Applications
        deployed using Corus absolutely do NOT need to depend on the server 
        module in any way. The artifact produced by this server is the actual
        Corus distribution.
      </p>
      <p>
        The above means the following:
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          Client applications linked to the Corus client classes are not bound 
          by the viral effect of the GPL. They depend entirely on classes 
          released under the Apache 2.0 license, the most liberal of all open 
          source license. It means that code linked to these classes does not
          require its source to be redistributed; that it can be proprietary;
          it also means that the Corus client .jar can be redistributed 
          without restrictions as part of client applications.
        </li>
        <li>
          For the server part, it means that no one can modify and redistribute 
          Corus without providing their entire modifications as source to their 
          customers; it also means that their modifications automatically become 
          subjected to the GPL. In addition, new software that is linked
          to the Corus server libraries automatically becomes subjected to the GPL.
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>
        In 99.9% of cases, this licensing scheme has no impact on the projects 
        using Corus: client applications will use the client classes, which 
        fall under the Apache 2.0 license, and are therefore shielded from any 
        viral licensing restrictions or obligations.
      </p>
      <p>
        We recommend that you read the 
        <a target="gpl_faq" href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html">GPL FAQ</a>
        if you have more questions.
      </p>
    </sapia:sect-desc>
  </sapia:sect1>
</sapia:page>
