<sapia:page cssPath="../css/sapia.css" title="Generic Linux Installtion" xmlns:sapia="http://www.sapia-oss.org/2003/XSL/Transform">

  <head>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="css/corus.css" type="text/css"/>
  </head>

  <sapia:vmenu>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus Home" href="../index.html"/>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus Guide" href="../guide/index.html"/>
    <sapia:vsection name="In 2 minutes" href="../overview.html"/> 
    <sapia:vsection name="REST API" href="../rest.html"/>    
    <sapia:vsection name="Docker" href="../guide/docker_integration.html"/>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus vs Chef" href="../corus_vs_chef.html"/>        
  </sapia:vmenu>
  
  <sapia:sect1 title="Generic Linux Installation">
    <sapia:section>
      <sapia:path name="home" href="../../../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="projects" />
      <sapia:path name="corus" href="../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="installation" href="../install.html" />
      <sapia:path name="generic linux installation" />
    </sapia:section>
    
    <sapia:sect-desc>
      <sapia:note>
      Corus is preferrably installed using the <a href="https://supermarket.chef.io/cookbooks/corus">Chef cookbook</a> (there is 
      <a href="https://github.com/sapia-oss/corus/tree/master/modules/thirdparty/chef/corus">exhaustive documentation</a> for the cookbook). 
      We're still providing instructions for manual installation below.
      </sapia:note>
    </sapia:sect-desc>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Preparing the Environment">
	    <sapia:sect-desc>
	     <p>There is a bit of preparation to do before actually extracting the Corus package.</p>
	    </sapia:sect-desc>

      <sapia:sect3 title="Java">
	      <p>
	        Before installing Corus you need to have Java installed on your machine. Corus requires at least Java 7. Also, Corus requires 
	        the presence of the <tt>$JAVA_HOME</tt> environment variable that points to the Java runtime you want to use (JRE or JDK).
	      </p>
      
      </sapia:sect3>    
      
      <sapia:sect3 title="Corus User">
        <p>
        Since Corus is mainly a background process, we strongly suggest that the Corus server be installed and executed with the privileges of a restricted user.
        Using the <tt>useradd</tt>, create a new system user named <tt>corus</tt>:
        </p>
        <sapia:code>sudo useradd corus</sapia:code>
        
        <p>
        Using the groupadd command, create a group to which the corus user will belong (or you may simply prefer to associate the corus user to an already existing group). 
        For example, creating an <tt>ops</tt> groups:
        </p>
        <sapia:code>sudo groupadd ops</sapia:code>
      
        <p>
        Associate the <tt>corus</tt> user to the group:
        </p>
        <sapia:code>sudo usermod -G ops corus</sapia:code>  
      </sapia:sect3>
      
      <sapia:sect3 title="Installation Directory">
        <p>
        Next, you need to create a directory on your system in which you will install Corus. For example:
        </p>
        <sapia:code>sudo mkdir /opt/corus</sapia:code>
      </sapia:sect3>
      
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Extract the Corus Package">
      <p>
        Extract the Corus distribution file into the Corus installation directory created above (adjust the Corus version number to match yours):
      </p>
      <sapia:code>sudo tar --directory=/opt/corus -xvf sapia_corus_server_package-5.0-linux64.tar.gz</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        You should now have the <code>/opt/corus/sapia_corus_server_package-5.0</code> directory. A good practice is to create a <tt>current</tt> symlink, and point
        it to the newly created directory:
      </p>
      <sapia:code>sudo ln -s /opt/corus/sapia_corus_server_package-5.0-linux64 /opt/corus/current</sapia:code>
    
      <p>
        Make sure you assign the ownership to the <tt>corus</tt> user:
      </p>
      <sapia:code>chown -R corus /opt/corus/current </sapia:code>
    </sapia:sect2>

    <sapia:sect2 title="Configure the Environment">
      <p>
        Corus requires a <tt>CORUS_HOME</tt> environment variable, which should point to the installation directory. 
        You must also add the <tt>bin</tt> directory under <tt>CORUS_HOME</tt> to the <tt>PATH</tt> environment variable. A good practice on Linux
        is to do all of this in a shell script (say, <tt>corus.sh</tt>) that you put under <tt>/etc/profile.d</tt>). The <tt>corus.sh</tt> script would 
        contain the following:
      </p>
      <sapia:code>export CORUS_HOME=/opt/corus/current
export PATH=$CORUS_HOME/bin:$PATH</sapia:code>
    
      <p>With the above setup, you should be able to run Corus manually, by simply typing <tt>corus</tt> in the terminal.</p>
   
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Configure Discovery">
      <p>Corus uses IP multicast for cluster discovery by default. But that method can be faulty (multicast might not be allowed in your network, or configured to
      go through routers), and it is typically not available in the cloud.</p>
      
      <p>Corus supports TCP-based discovery: the different supported mechanisms (and their respective configuration) is explained in the <a href="../guide/discovery.html">Discovery</a>
      section. Please consult that section for the details.</p>
    
    </sapia:sect2>
      
    <sapia:sect2 title="Run as a Daemon">
      <p>
       A script is available to register Corus as a system service. It is found under the following path: <tt>$CORUS_HOME/bin/corus.init.d-nowrapper</tt>
       and copy it under the  <tt>/etc/init.d</tt> directory and name it <tt>corus</tt>:
      </p>
      <sapia:code>sudo cp $CORUS_HOME/current/bin/corus.init.d-nowrapper /etc/init.d/corus</sapia:code>
      
      <p>The use your editor (vi, vim, etc.) to set the <tt>JAVA_HOME</tt>, <tt>CORUS_HOME</tt> and <tt>CORUS_GROUP</tt> variables 
      (set the group to the one to which you've assigned the <tt>corus</tt> user).</p>
    </sapia:sect2> 
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Register with the Run Levels">
      <p>
        This part of the procedure may vary according to the Linux flavor you're using. We're describing the steps for RedHat flavors (RedHat, Centos, Fedora).
      </p>
      <p>Execute the <tt>chkconfig</tt> command:</p>
      
      <sapia:code>sudo chkconfig --add /etc/init.d/corus</sapia:code>
      
      <p>You can validate the run level registration as follows:</p>
      
      <sapia:code>sudo chkconfig --list | grep corus
corus 0:off 1:off 2:on 3:on 4:on 5:on 6:off</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
      As you can see upon installation, the Corus service is not running. You can start it using the <tt>service</tt> command, as follows:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>sudo service corus start</sapia:code>
    
      <p>Once you start the Corus service, you can validate its proper execution by looking at the Corus log files under the <tt>$CORUS_HOME/logs</tt>
        directory.</p>
        
      <p>You can also start the Corus CLI (Command Line Interface) to connect to the server. Simply type <tt>coruscli</tt> in a terminal window: 
      this will connect you to the Corus instance running locally.</p>
      
     </sapia:sect2> 
  </sapia:sect1>
</sapia:page>
