<sapia:page title="Exploring the Corus Command-Line" 
  cssPath="../css/sapia.css" 
  xmlns:sapia="http://www.sapia-oss.org/2003/XSL/Transform">

  <head>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="../css/corus.css" type="text/css"/>
  </head>

  <sapia:vmenu>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus Home" href="../index.html"/>
    <sapia:vsection name="Tutorials" href="index.html"/>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus Guide" href="../guide/index.html"/>
  </sapia:vmenu>

  <sapia:sect1 title="Exploring the Corus Command-Line">
    <sapia:section>
      <sapia:path name="home" href="../../../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="projects" />
      <sapia:path name="corus" href="../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="learning" href="../learning.html" />
      <sapia:path name="tutorials" href="index.html"/>
      <sapia:path name="exploring the command-line" />
    </sapia:section>

    <sapia:sect-desc>
      <p>
        You've had quite a good overview of the Corus CLI in the 
        <a href="webapp.html">introductory tutorial</a>. Now it's time for
        a more in-depth look.
      </p>
      <p>
        The CLI provides an array of commands, used to manage distributions,
        processes, and Corus itself.
      </p>
      <p>
        In this section, we're presenting you with the CLI's main features.
      </p>
    </sapia:sect-desc>

    <sapia:sect2 title="A Note on the Architecture">
      <p>
        The command-line is just a front-end that itself wraps usage of the
        remote interface provided by the Corus server, allowing it to be 
        managed over the network.
      </p>
      <p>
        In fact, the CLI internally uses a "facade" that hides the details
        of using the remote interface. One could use the facade to implement
        their own management frontend, for example.
      </p>
      <p>
        Through the facade, the CLI connects to a Corus server over
        the network. The commands that are typed at the command-line are 
        converted to object form - in fact, to remote method calls that
        are processed by Corus.
      </p>
    </sapia:sect2>

    <toc/>    

    <sapia:sect2 title="Obtaining On-line Documentation">
      <p>
        The CLI supports an array of commands. A lot of these commands
        will look familiar to you since they mimick the Linux/Unix ones. 
      </p>

      <sapia:note>This characteristic is intentional: it was one of our main
      goals to get sysadmins up and running rapidly, since they're the ones
      making the deployments in production. It is our experience that after
      getting used to Corus, you'll type common Linux commands in the CLI and
      wonder why they're not working, then realizing that you're indeed
      using the CLI...</sapia:note>

      <p>
        The most basic and important command is 
        <sapia:command>man</sapia:command>, which, as in Linux/Unix, allows
        displaying help about a specific command. Just typing 
        <sapia:command>man</sapia:command> without any arguments will display
        the categorized list of commands. To obtain help about a specific
        command, type <sapia:command>man</sapia:command> followed by the actual
        name of the command whose help you want displayed.
      </p>

      <p>
        You'll see that the help not only documents the syntax of a command,
        but also provides examples illustrating different scenarios. 
        To obtain details about a command, the online help is your best friend.
      </p>

    </sapia:sect2>

    <sapia:sect2 title="Experimenting">
      <p>
        For the sake of practice, we'll go through the deployment of your
        <a href="webapp.html">Grails web app</a> again, and explore the CLI in 
        a more in-depth manner.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        As a first step, start a Corus instance on your workstation. Then 
        connect to it with the CLI (note that the options for the host
        and port are not required when connecting to localhost, on the default
        Corus port):
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>coruscli -h localhost -p 33000</sapia:code>

      <p>
        Now deploy the distribution:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>deploy target/corus_sample_jetty-<sapia:param value="project.version"/>-basic.zip</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        As you've seen previously, you can use <sapia:command>ls</sapia:command>
        to view the list of currently deployed distributions. The 
        <sapia:command>ls</sapia:command> command also takes options that allow
        filtering the results (in cases where you have many distributions with
        different names and/or versions). Type 
        <sapia:command>man ls</sapia:command> to view the options that the
        command takes.
      </p>
      
      
      <p>
        Of course there's only one distribution deployed now, so there's not
        much to filter. But just for the sake of showing that it works, type 
        the following as is:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>ls -d foo</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        No distribution is listed, confirming that the filtering works... Now type:
      </p>

      <sapia:code>ls -d basic-sample-jetty -v 5.0</sapia:code>

      <p>
        Nothing again: no 
        <sapia:command>basic-sample-jetty</sapia:command> version matches 
        the one specified.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Now this:
      </p>

      <sapia:code>ls -d basic-sample-jetty -v 1.0</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        Our distribution appears.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        As you've seen in the <a href="webapp.html">Grails web app</a> tutorial,
        the <sapia:command>exec</sapia:command> command also takes such options.
        For example:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>exec -d basic-sample-jetty -v 1.0 -v 1.0 -n server -p dev</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        The above starts the process corresponding to the given options, 
        that is: the "server" process (or, the process with the "server" 
        <sapia:command>n</sapia:command>ame) of the "basic-sample-jetty" 
        distribution version "1.0", under the "dev" profile.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        The same can be said of the <sapia:command>kill</sapia:command> command:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>kill -d basic-sample-jetty -v 1.0 -n server -p dev</sapia:code>

      <p>
        And similarly for the undeploy command: 
      </p>

      <sapia:code>undeploy -d basic-sample-jetty -v 1.0</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        The above commands are convenient, but can prove counter-productive when
        having to perform operations on multiple distributions or processes,
        which is often required in the context of deployment. The next section 
        explores the solution to this problem. 
      </p>
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Wildcards">
      <p>
        Most command specifying options for filtering results also support
        wildcard matching. A concrete example will demonstrate this:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>exec -d basic* -v * -n * -p dev</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        The above would target processes with any name, of distributions whose
        name starts with "basic", of any version, under profile "dev" (note
        that the profile option does not support wildcards).
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Wildcard matching greatly improves productivity: imagine that a bunch
        of processes corresponding to a given distribution version are 
        currently running, and that the deployment of a new version must be
        performed. You can use wilcards to optimize your manipulations. 
        The following illustrates a sequence of commands corresponding to this
        scenario:
      </p>
      
<sapia:code>kill -d * -v * -n * -w
undeploy -d * -v *
deploy target/corus_sample_jetty*.zip</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        Consult the CLI's online help for more details about how each command
        supports wildcards.
      </p>
    
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Command Clustering">
      <p>
        Although Corus clustering is not the subject of this tutorial, it is
        still relevant to mention it in the context of commands. Indeed, it
        is possible to execute commands not only "on" the Corus instance to
        which the CLI is currently connected, but on all instances in the cluster
        (or domain).
      </p>
      
      <p>
        To "cluster" a command, one only needs specifiying the 
        <sapia:command>-cluster</sapia:command> option at the end of the 
        command-line, such as in:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>exec -d corus* -v * -n * -p dev -cluster</sapia:code>

      <p>
        This will start the process corresponding to the specified options
        on all Corus instances in the domain (provided they have the 
        corresponding distribution).
      </p>
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Conclusion">
      <p>
        In this tutorial, you've had a more in-depth look at the command-line
        interface. We suggest you explore the CLI's help. Have look at each 
        command, especially the examples.
      </p>
    </sapia:sect2>

  </sapia:sect1>
</sapia:page>
