<sapia:page title="Corus Tutorials" cssPath="../css/sapia.css" 
  xmlns:sapia="http://www.sapia-oss.org/2003/XSL/Transform">

  <head>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="../css/corus.css" type="text/css"/>
  </head>
  

  <sapia:vmenu>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus Home" href="../index.html"/>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus Guide" href="../guide/index.html"/>
  </sapia:vmenu>

  <sapia:sect1 title="Tutorials">
    <sapia:section>
      <sapia:path name="home" href="../../../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="projects" />
      <sapia:path name="corus"     href="../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="learning"  href="../learning.html" />
      <sapia:path name="tutorials" />
    </sapia:section>

    <sapia:sect-desc>
      <p>
        We've designed tutorials that provide a gradual introduction to Corus.
        We suggest you follow the tutorials in the order in which they're
        presented below. We also suggest you read the 
        <a href="../guide/index.html">Corus Guide</a>.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        In order to go through the tutorials, you'll have to check out Corus
        and <a href="building.html">build it from source</a> - that is in fact 
        the subject of the first tutorial.
      </p>
    
      <div>
        <div class="article-box">
          <h1><a href="building.html">1) Building from Source</a></h1> 
          All other tutorials are based on sample applications that are part
          of the Corus source tree. You need to build Corus from source in order
          to move on to the other tutorials. We're showing you how in this 
          tutorial.
        </div>
        
        <div class="article-box">
          <h1><a href="webapp.html">2) Web App Example</a></h1> 
          See how a Grails web app is deployed into a Jetty container that is
          itself deployed into Corus. The tutorials illustrate the full
          development-to-deployment cycle. At the end of this tutorial you'll
          have a very good grasp of what Corus is about.
        </div>
        
        <div class="article-box">
          <h1><a href="corus-descriptor.html">3) The Corus Descriptor</a></h1> 
          What is it exactly? How is it used? The descriptor tells Corus 
          how to start your applications. It's the only Corus-specific config 
          file you'll need when deploying standalone Java apps into Corus.
        </div>
      </div>
      
      <div style="clear: both;" />

      <div>
        <div class="article-box">
          <h1><a href="exploring-cli.html">4) Exploring the CLI</a></h1> 
          The command-line interface mimicks Linux/Unix commands and is
          the primary tool through which you interact with Corus.
          Explore the various features, play around with wildcards,
          learn about clustered commands. 
        </div>
        
        <div class="article-box">
          <h1><a href="corus-domain.html">5) Managing a Corus Domain</a></h1> 
          The real power of Corus lies in its "collective management" 
          capabilities. You can manage a whole domain of Corus instances through
          the Corus command-line, without more hassle than you do a single 
          instance.
        </div>
        
        <div class="article-box">
          <h1><a href="advanced-management.html">6) Advanced Management</a></h1> 
          There are more features in stores to streamline deployments and 
          ease the pain of maintenance operations. In this tutorial, we're 
          exploring these hassle-saving features. 
        </div>
      </div>
      
    </sapia:sect-desc>
    
  </sapia:sect1>
</sapia:page>
