<sapia:page title="Web App Example" cssPath="../css/sapia.css"
  xmlns:sapia="http://www.sapia-oss.org/2003/XSL/Transform">

  <head>
    <script type="text/javascript" src="http://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.4/jquery.min.js"></script>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="../css/corus.css" type="text/css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="../shadowbox-3.0.3/shadowbox.css" />
    <script type="text/javascript" src="../shadowbox-3.0.3/shadowbox.js"></script>
    <script type="text/javascript">
    Shadowbox.init();
    </script>
  </head>

  <sapia:vmenu>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus Home" href="../index.html"/>
    <sapia:vsection name="Tutorials" href="index.html"/>
    <sapia:vsection name="Corus Guide" href="../guide/index.html"/>
  </sapia:vmenu>
  
  <sapia:sect1 title="Web App Example">
    <sapia:section>
      <sapia:path name="home" href="../../../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="projects" />
      <sapia:path name="corus"     href="../home.html" />
      <sapia:path name="learning"  href="../learning.html" />
      <sapia:path name="tutorials" href="index.html"/>
      <sapia:path name="web app example" />
    </sapia:section>
    
    <sapia:sect-desc>
      <p>
        The goal of this tutorial is to provide you with a clear picture of 
        the development-to-deployment cycle that is implied by using Corus.
      </p>
      <p>
        The tutorial consists of a simple web application, deployed into an
        embedded Jetty container, which is itself started by Corus.
      </p>
      <p>
        As you'll be able to see by yourself, Corus allows deploying plain Java 
        standalone apps (that is: applications that are bootstrapped by a class 
        with a <sapia:command>main()</sapia:command> method).
      </p>
    </sapia:sect-desc>
    
    <toc/>    
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="The code">
      <p>
        An you've seen in the <a href="building.html">previous tutorial</a>
        The source code is built with Maven and separated into two modules:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
          The module for the web application per say.
        </li>
        <li>
          The module for the embedded Jetty container distribution that 
          includes the above web app, and is deployed into Corus.
        </li>
      </ul>

      <p>      
        We're using Grails' <a target="grails-maven" href="http://grails.org/doc/latest/guide/4.%20The%20Command%20Line.html#4.5%20Ant%20and%20Maven">Maven support</a> 
        in order to build the webapp, which is the one corresponding to the
        <a target="grails-tutorial" href="http://www.grails.org/Quick+Start">Grails tutorial</a>).
      </p>
      
      <sapia:note>
        In order to follow the manipulations at the command-line that are described
        in this tutorial, cd under the <sapia:command>corus_sample_jetty</sapia:command>
        directory of the Corus source tree, as it was described <a href="building.html#samples_structure">here</a>.
      </sapia:note>
      
      <p>
        That being said, we'll now see the module from which we'll create a 
        Corus distribution. Part of that module, an embedded Jetty container in 
        a simple standalone Java class:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>package org.sapia.corus.sample.jetty;

import org.eclipse.jetty.server.Server;

public class BasicJettyServer {

  public static void main(String[] args) throws Exception{
    EmbeddedServer embedded = new EmbeddedServer(8080);
    embedded.start();
  }
}
      </sapia:code>

      <p>
        The server expects web applications to be present under the directory 
        correspdonding to <sapia:command>${user.dir}/webapps</sapia:command>,
        where <sapia:command>${user.dir}</sapia:command> corresponds to the
        <a target="user-dir" href="http://www.roseindia.net/java/example/java/io/GetCurrentDir.shtml">matching JVM property</a>. 
        If you dig into the code, you will see that the bulk of the logic of loading the webapps
        is isolated within a <sapia:class>ServerUtil</sapia:class> class, 
        that loads the war files (or exploded war directories) under 
        <sapia:command>webapps</sapia:command> as web applications into the 
        Jetty container. Therefore, our server expects the war for our Grails 
        application to be present under its 
        <sapia:command>webapps</sapia:command> directory.
      </p>
      <p>
        That's exactly how the distribution of our Jetty server that is meant 
        for deployment into Corus is packaged. The distribution is built using
        a Maven assembly. Its directory layout is given below:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>/
  META-INF/
    corus.xml
  lib/
    ... the server's dependency jars ...
  webapps/
    corus_sample_grails_app-<sapia:param value="project.version" />.war</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        So the distribution is packaged following the same directory structure
        we're using when we're developping:
      </p>
      
      <center><img src="img/local_layout.png" /></center>
      <p/>
      <sapia:note>
       To build the embedded Jetty server distributions that are used in the
       context of the tutorials, do a <sapia:command>mvn install</sapia:command> 
       in the <sapia:command>corus_sample_jetty</sapia:command> directory.
      </sapia:note>
    
      <p>
        We'll see later on what the <sapia:command>corus.xml</sapia:command> file is
        used for. For now you can actually run the server in your IDE. And 
        <b>that's the point:</b> test the code entirely and thoroughly, on the 
        development workstation, prior to deploying into Corus.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        For example, to load the project in Eclipse, type the following maven
        command in the server module's root:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>mvn eclipse:eclipse</sapia:code>    
      
      <p>
        Then create the project in Eclipse (use the "create from existing
        sources" option). Your layout should be as follows: 
      </p>
      
      <center><img src="img/eclipse-layout.png" /></center>
      
      
      <p>
        Once the setup is done, just right-click on the 
        <sapia:class>BasicJettyServer</sapia:class> class and choose the
        "Run as Java Application" option. The server should start and you
        should be able to connect to the application at the following URL:
      </p>
      
      
      <sapia:tag name="a">  
        <sapia:attr name="href">
          <sapia:text>http://localhost:8080/corus_sample_grails_app-</sapia:text><sapia:param name="project.version" />
        </sapia:attr><sapia:text>http://localhost:8080/corus_sample_grails_app-</sapia:text><sapia:param name="project.version" />
      </sapia:tag>
      
    </sapia:sect2>

    <sapia:sect2 title="Configuration">
      <p>
      Now that the application source code is ready, we need to prepare our 
      embedded Jetty module for deployment into Corus. There are two things
      to remember:
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          Applications deployed into Corus must be packaged in a zip archive
          (called a "distribution" in Corus terminology).
        </li>
        <li>
          The archive must contain a Corus descriptor (a file named 
          <sapia:command>corus.xml</sapia:command>) that is stored under a
          <sapia:command>META-INF</sapia:command> directory of the archive).
        </li>
      </ol>

      <p>
      In our case, here is the Corus descriptor for our application
      (we discuss the descriptor format more thoroughly 
      <a href="corus-descriptor.html">here</a>):
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code><![CDATA[
<distribution name="basic-sample-jetty" version="1.0" xmlns="http://www.sapia-oss.org/xsd/corus/distribution-5.0.xsd">
  <process  name="server" 
            maxKillRetry="3" 
            shutdownTimeout="30000" 
            invoke="true">
    <java mainClass="org.sapia.corus.sample.jetty.BasicJettyServer"
          profile="dev" vmType="server">
      <xoption  name="ms" value="16M" />
    </java>
    <java mainClass="org.sapia.corus.sample.jetty.BasicJettyServer"
          profile="prod" vmType="server">
      <xoption  name="ms" value="128M" />
    </java>
  </process> 
</distribution>]]>
      </sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        As we've mentioned previously, using a Maven assembly, we package our 
        distribution so that it contains:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
          The Corus descriptor under the <sapia:command>META-INF</sapia:command> 
          directory;
        </li>
        <li>
          the jar containing the compiled source of our class that starts 
          Jetty;
        </li>
        <li>
          the war dependency holding the resources of our webapp itself;
        </li>
        <li>
          the jar dependencies required to run Jetty.
        </li>
      </ul>
      
      <p>
        In short, we must package as part of the distribution all the resources 
        that are required in our application's classpath, in addition to the
        Corus descriptor.
      </p>
      
    </sapia:sect2>
      
    <sapia:sect2 title="Deploying the application's distribution">
      <p>
        Now that our distribution has been properly packaged, we need to 
        deploy it into Corus. First of all, make sure that you have a Corus
        instance running.
      </p> 
      
      <p>
        Once that's done, you can connect to Corus using the command-line
        interface. Type: <sapia:command>coruscli</sapia:command>.
      </p>      
      
      <p>
        The command-line interface will attempt connecting on a Corus instance
        running on localhost and port 33000 (which is the Corus default port).
        You can specify the host explicitely through the 
        <sapia:command>h</sapia:command> option, and the port through the
        <sapia:command>p</sapia:command> option, as in the following:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>coruscli -h localhost -p 33000</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        Upon successfully connecting to the Corus instance, the CLI 
        displays a <a href="img/coruscli_welcome.png" title="Corus CLI welcome screen" rel="shadowbox">welcome screen</a>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        To deploy the distribution, use the 
        <sapia:command>deploy</sapia:command> command, as follows:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>deploy target/corus_sample_jetty-<sapia:param value="project.version"/>-basic.zip</sapia:code>
            
      <p>
        Once the deployment has completed, you can see the list of
        distributions that are currently deployed  
        <a href="img/distribution_list.png" title="Listing distributions" rel="shadowbox">using the <sapia:command>ls</sapia:command> command</a>.
      </p>
      
      <sapia:note>
        As you've probably noticed, we've been completely free as to what 
        framework we use for development. Developing in the context of Corus
        means that you suffer no limitations or constraints with regards to 
        multi-threading, "bean pooling", etc. What you deploy into Corus are
        plain-old Java standalone apps. The only thing to add is the Corus 
        descriptor, which tells Corus about the applications contained in the 
        distribution and provides runtime JVM parameters.
      </sapia:note>
      
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Starting the server">
      <p>
        The natural thing to do now is to start an instance of the server. One
        uses the <sapia:command>exec</sapia:command> to that end:
      </p>
      <sapia:code>exec -d basic-sample-jetty -v 1.0 -n server -p dev</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        The <a href="img/exec_output.png" title="Starting a process" rel="shadowbox">output of the command</a> 
        indicates that Corus will proceed to the process' startup. To confirm 
        that this indeed has occured, type <sapia:command>ps</sapia:command> in 
        the CLI.
      </p>
      
      <sapia:note>
        If you look at <a href="img/process_list.png" title="Listing processes" rel="shadowbox">the listed process</a>
        you'll see there are two identifiers associated to it:
        <ul>
          <li>One is generated by Corus; it's the "Corus process identifier".</li>
          <li>The other is the actual process identifier generated by the OS.</li>
        </ul>
        
        Both of these identifiers can be used later on for referring to a
        specific process.
      </sapia:note>
      
      <p>
        Now, time to connect to our web app. Type the following URL in a browser:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:tag name="a">  
        <sapia:attr name="href">
          <sapia:text>http://localhost:8080/corus_sample_grails_app-</sapia:text><sapia:param name="project.version" />
        </sapia:attr><sapia:text>http://localhost:8080/corus_sample_grails_app-</sapia:text><sapia:param name="project.version" />
      </sapia:tag>
      
      <p>That's it, your first app managed by Corus.</p>
      
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Stopping the server">
      <p>
        To stop a process in Corus, use the <sapia:command>kill</sapia:command>
        command - which also allows stopping multiple processes at once, 
        using wildcards (we'll see that in 
        <a href="exploring-cli.html">another tutorial</a>). In our case, the
        process identifier assigned by the OS is 2807, so we can use terminate
        the server process like so:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>kill -op 2807</sapia:code>
      <p>
        The <sapia:command>op</sapia:command> switch stands for "OS process".
        (do a <sapia:command>man kill</sapia:command> in
        the CLI for more information about the command).
      </p>
      <sapia:note>
        Note that if you kill the process through the OS (that is, by using
        the OS' actual <sapia:command>kill</sapia:command>), Corus will
        restart the process automatically, as part of its high-availability
        feature).
      </sapia:note>
      
      <p>
        Once a kill is issued, Corus proceeds to the termination of the process
        or group of processes. In our case, Corus will proceed to the 
        termination of the Jetty server instance.
      </p>
      <p>
        When you type <sapia:command>ps</sapia:command> in the CLI, you should
        see the process status change (it goes from active mode to 
        <a href="img/process_kill_state.png" title="Process in shutdown" rel="shadowbox">shutdown mode</a>).
        Once termination of the process is confirmed, Corus removes it from
        its list, and it should therefore disappear from the output of the
        <sapia:command>ps</sapia:command> command. That's what happens to our
        Jetty server process - you can type <sapia:command>ps</sapia:command>
        repetitively in the CLI to see this happening.
      </p>
    
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Undeploying the distribution">
      <p>
        For the sake of completeness, we'll "undeploy" our Jetty server
        distribution from Corus. The <sapia:command>undeploy</sapia:command>
        command is used to that end:
      </p>
      
      <sapia:code>undeploy -d basic-sample-jetty -v 1.0</sapia:code>
      
      <p>
        After having undeployed, type <sapia:command>ls</sapia:command>. The 
        distribution should have disappeared.
      </p>
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    <sapia:sect2 title="Conclusion">
      <p>
        You've experienced in this tutorial the full development-to-deployment
        lifecycle implied by using Corus. You have also familiarized 
        yourself with the Corus CLI, which as you'll soon see, allows not
        only managing a single Corus daemon, but a whole domain.
      </p>
    </sapia:sect2>
    
    
  </sapia:sect1>
</sapia:page>
